John H. Crider Papers
John H. Crider Papers
1868-1966
Crider, John Henshaw, 1906-
2.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American newspaper journalist, editor, and author. Collection includes correspondence (1925-1966); research files; and writings, including articles, book outlines and manuscripts, editorials, essays, and speeches.
148915
Biographical History
John H. Crider (1906-??) was an American newspaper journalist, editor, and author. While at the Boston Herald he won the 1949 Pulitzer Prize for Journalism for distinguished editorial writing.
Born in Mount Vernon, New York, Crider attended the Virginia Military Institute and the Pulitzer School of Journalism at Columbia University. He was one of two seniors in the School of Journalism who were the first students to be given a part-time job on the city staff of the New York Times during their senior year. He was a Nieman Fellow at Harvard University (1940-1941).
Crider served on the news staff of the New York Times for 19 years. The last ten were spent with its Washington Bureau where he covered the White House during the latter years of Franklin D. Roosevelt's presidency. From 1946 to 1951 Crider was editor-in-chief of the Boston Herald, where his editorial writing won several award including a Pulitzer Prize (for "distinguished editorial writing") in 1949. He also appeared on two regular television programs in Boston and for a time was a CBS news analyst for that city.
In 1959 Crider was a member of the United States delegation to the Atlantic Conference in London where a paper of his, proposing an economic program for the NATO nations, was an important item on the agenda.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John H. Crider Papers consist of biographical material, memorabilia, printed material, subjects files, and writings.
Memorabilia contains photographs and Crider's war correspondent license for 1956.
Subject files include correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and miscellaneous printed material. Notable correspondents include Dwight D. Eisenhower, Lyndon B. Johnson, and Robert Frost. Also included in the collection is a signed letter from Horace Greeley, owned by Crider.
Writings contains articles, books, editorials, essays, speeches, and miscellaneous other writings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Subject files are arranged alphabetically. Writings are subdivided by type and arranged within that by title.
Related Material
has several manuscript collections of noted journalists and war correspondents. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Crider, John Henshaw, 1906-, -- Archives.; Authors, American.; Journalism -- Authorship.; Journalists -- United States.; Newspaper editors -- United States.; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc. -- Editorials.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Editorials.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical data
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Barron's National Business and Financial Weekly, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Bell, Elliott V., 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - Byrd, Richard E. (Admiral), 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Coatesville Conference on Economic Freedoms, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University School of Journalism, 1937-1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1966; undated; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Crider's first assignment, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Douglas, William O., 1940-1952 (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1949-1953 (Box 1)
  - Freedom of the press, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Gillis, Ann, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - Gruenther, Alfred M., 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Herter, Christian A., 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Horace Greeley letter, 1868 (Box 1)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - International Chamber of Commerce Editorial Award, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Jesse, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Krock, Arthur, 1941-1964 (Box 1)
  - Lippincott, J. B. and Co., 1952 (Box 1)
  - Lyons-Kennedy incident, 1940 (Box 1)
  - National Military Establishment, Joint Civilian Orientation Conference, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Nevins, Allan, Mandate for Change, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Nieman Fellows, 1939-1963 (Box 1)
  - Nigeria, 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Norwood Housing Trust (George F. Willett), 1927-1952 (Box 1)
  - Pitkin formula, psychology of reader interest (Box 1)
  - Port Said assignment (Box 1)
  - Pries, Harold, 1948-1955 (Box 1)
  - Pulitzer Prize, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - Raymond Clapper Memorial Award, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Reader's Digest, 1943-1962 (Box 1)
  - Resignation from Boston Herald, 1951-1952; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Robie, Richard S., 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Saltonstall, Leverett (Senator), 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  - Sigma Delta Chi Award, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1940-1955 (Box 1)
  - Talouselama Economic Weekly, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Television and radio, 1950-1954 (Box 1)
  - Thank-you letters, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - TWA Press Flight, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - United Nations Monetary and Financial Conference, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Vinson, Fred, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Western trip, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Whaley, P. H., 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Wigglesworth, Richard B., 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Willoughby, Woodbury, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Wright, John (Bishop), 1947-1954 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Rejected (Box 2)
  - Articles for magazines (by publication title)
    - America; The American; The American Mercury; Barron's, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - The Bulletin; The Cadet; The Concord Journal (Box 2)
    - Editor and Publisher; Finance; The Freeman; Goegraphical Magazine; International News Service (Box 2)
    - Issues; Nation's Business; New York Times; Nieman Reports (Box 2)
    - Reader's Digest; The Republican; Saturday Review; Scientific American; Tax Magazine (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Being a newspaperman, draft (Box 2)
    - The bureaucrat, circa 1944; published material (Box 2)
    - Can we survive the sixties as free men, outline (Box 2)
    - Government by deceit, outline, typescript (Box 2)
    - Just about people, typescript (Box 2)
    - New world rising, rough draft (Box 2)
    - Untitled, 2 folders; typescript (Box 2)
    - The White House years, page proofs, incomplete (Box 2)
  - Editorials
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Essays
    - A-S, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - T-W (Box 3)
  - Miscellany
    - Assorted writings (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - Miscellaneous, 1941-1954; 2 folders (Box 3)